Today is דף י *Daf Yud*. We start in the middle of
ט עמוד ב *Tet Amud Bet* at the, where are we?
תנו רבנן tanu rabanan *Tanu Rabbanan* we're on the top.
תנו רבנן Rabbanan
*Tanu
Rabbanan* where were we?
Thank you.
So yeah, not in the middle. It's near the top of ט
עמוד ב *Tet Amud Bet* about ten lines down. תנו רבנן *Tanu
Rabbanan*. Okay, so we're talking about again women who are מסולקת דמים
mesuleket damim, *Mesuleket Damim*, who are not usually expecting to get their
period, so if they when they find out they bled they're not
concerned about what might have happened before. And we're now dealing with
a woman who is at the period of being post-menopausal.
So let's take a look. תנו רבנן זקנה שעברו עליה שלוש עונות
וראתה ve-ra'asah, *Tanu Rabbanan zekenah she-avru aleiha shalosh onot ve-ra'atah*. So an
elderly woman, who we described what that was yesterday, somebody who's beginning
to appear old and now they went three periods, which means ninety
days without having had three cycles, I should say, without having had
her period, without bleeding. וראתה ve-ra'asah. *Ve-ra'atah*, so at this moment now
that she went ninety days, she's considered מסולקת דמים mesuleket damim. *Mesuleket
Damim*. So she sees, דייה שעתה *Dayah Sha'atah*, the הלכה halacha *Halakha*
is that she is only worried from that moment on, she doesn't
have to be worried back twenty-four hours based on what we just
said. Now though, it's not the end of the story. ועוד עברו
עליה שלוש עונות וראתה *Ve-od avru aleiha shalosh onot ve-ra'atah*. Now there's
another ninety days that passed and she sees again. Because you'll remember
the הלכה halacha *Halakha* is that once a woman bleeds having been
in this state, whatever the various states are that she is מסולקת
דמים mesuleket damim *Mesuleket Damim*, then it's evidence that she is no
longer מסולקת דמים mesuleket damim *Mesuleket Damim* and she actually is still
bleeding. So if she had bled a second time right afterwards, thirty
days later, we would have said twenty-four hours. But what happened? She
didn't bleed thirty days later. She went another ninety days. So having
gone another ninety days, it restores her status as מסולקת דמים mesuleket
damim. *Mesuleket Damim*. Is everybody sort of with me? Right? She went
ninety days during a period when she was already older without bleeding.
That proved she was post-menopausal, she was מסולקת דמים mesuleket damim *Mesuleket
Damim*. She bled once. That would have been counter-evidence and that would
have said, "Ah, now we see she's not מסולקת דמים mesuleket damim,
*Mesuleket Damim* if she bleeds again twenty-four hours back." But what happened
was, she didn't bleed again right away within thirty days or within
whatever, she bled again ninety days later. So having waited the ninety
days again was again a proof that she was once more מסולקת
דמים mesuleket damim. *Mesuleket Damim*. So once again when she bleeds, it
again is the הלכה halachah, *Halakha* of דייה שעתה *Dayah Sha'atah*.
The same thing happens a third time. And then now she has
a new עונה *Onah* for everything.
Very good. ועוד עברו עליה שלוש עונות *Ve-od avru aleiha shalosh onot*,
now she went another ninety days, now you would say, "Oh, another
ninety days it starts again. Now it's also דייה שעתה *Dayah Sha'atah*,
she once again is מסולקת דמים mesuleket damim *Mesuleket Damim*." וראתה *Ve-ra'atah*,
no, Michael guessed it, הרי היא ככל הנשים *Harei hi ke-chol ha-nashim*.
Now she is not מסולקת דמים mesuleket damim, *Mesuleket Damim*. Why? Because
now she's established a pattern. What's her pattern? She bleeds every ninety
days. So now she is considered to not be מסולקת דמים mesuleket
damim *Mesuleket Damim*, just be a woman with a very long pattern.
ומטמאות מעת לעת ומפקידה לפקידה *U-metame'ot me-et le-et u-mi-pekidah li-pekidah* and she's
concerned backwards twenty-four hours or since the last time she checked. I
mean my understanding is when women are getting to become post-menopausal, their
cycles are all out of whack and sometimes it changes, whatever. I
don't know if it goes as much as ninety days. But anyway,
but that would have established her pattern. Okay. ולא *Ve-lo*, and now
it goes on to say, ולא שקבעה אלא Ela אפילו פחתה והותירה
*Ve-lo she-kave'ah ela afilu pichtah ve-hotirah*. Not and again there's a question
about whether the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will analyze this in a minute.
Not that she was exact, ninety days, ninety days, ninety days, or
not only that she was exact, but even if she was inexact,
even if once it was ninety days, next was ninety-two days, ninety-four
days. Sort of
going up, right?
In increment to either way.
Okay, so let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going
to analyze why that would matter. So let's look at what the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. אפילו פחתה ולא מיבעיא קבעה *Afilu pichtah ve-lo
miba'ya kave'ah*? What? You're saying even if she was inexact then we
would start being concerned, but it goes without saying that if she
was exact? אדרבה adaraba, *Adarabba*, the opposite makes sense. כי קבעה קבעה
לה וסת kav'ah lah veset, ודייה שעתה *Ki kave'ah kav'ah lah veset
ve-dayah sha'atah*. If she's exact, it's a different הלכה halachah? *Halakha*. If
she is, it's, you know, you're making it sound like if it
was exact it's obvious we start worrying twenty-four hours. But if she
varies maybe it's not so obvious. גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says the opposite
is true. If she's exact, what did our first משנה mishna *Mishnah*
say? Our first משנה *Mishnah* said that a woman that has an
exact period, who has a וסת קבוע veseit kavua, *Veset Kavua*, if
she bleeds during when she's expecting her period, then she isn't concerned
backwards. She's only concerned because she expects it will happen when she
has her expected period. So this ברייתא braita *Baraita* said this woman
that went ninety days, ninety days, ninety days, now she has to
worry twenty-four hours back. Oh, and not only in the case of
exact, even inexact. What do you mean not only in the case
of exact? When it's exact she doesn't have to worry back because
then she has a regular period. So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says,
אדרבה כי קבעה קבעה לה וסת ודייה שעתה *Adarabba ki kave'ah kav'ah
lah veset ve-dayah sha'atah*. If she's exact ninety days, ninety days, then
she doesn't have to worry, then she has a regular וסת *Veset*,
a regular cycle, and she's not concerned backwards twenty-four hours. וכי תימא
רבנן היא דפליגי עליה דרבי דוסא דאמר אשה שיש לה וסת
מטמאה מעת לעת *Ve-ki teima rabbanan hi de-pleigi aleih de-Rabbi Dosa de-amar
ishah she-yesh lah veset metame'ah me-et le-et*. fixed cycle when she bleeds
even on her expected period is concerned 24 hours, fine, the הלכה
halachah? might be that that woman is concerned, but still, being exact
is still less of a meaning it is still more of a
חידוש chiddush that you're חושש choshesh when you're exact than when you're
inexact. איפכא מיבעי ליה, Ipcha miba'ei lei, it should have said the
opposite. לימא לא שפחתה והותירה, Leima, lo she-pachsa ve-hotira, not only is
she concerned when she's inexact backwards 24 hours, אלא אפילו כיוונה, ela
afilu kivna, even if it's exact, 90 days, 90 days, 90 days,
where there is a reason to say she wouldn't be concerned, nevertheless
she still is. So the language of the ברייתא braita is wrong.
The ברייתא braita should have said not only is she concerned 24
hours back when she's inexact, she should even be concerned when she's
exact or she shouldn't be concerned when she's exact. But it's not
the way we have it phrased, which takes it that it's more
obvious she's concerned when she is exact than when she's inexact. So
the גמרא gemara says fine, switch it, לא תני הכי, lo tani
hachi, change the language, לא שפחתה והותירה אלא אפילו כיוונה. lo she-pachsa
ve-hotira ela afilu kivna. Fine,
switch the language, have it saying not only when she's inexact, even
when she's exact. So the הלכה halacha is still the same, whether
exact or inexact she's concerned 24 hours, but we're just clearer that
there is less of a reason to say that when she's exact.
When she's exact, you would say maybe we don't have to be
concerned backwards, she bled when she was expecting to bleed. And nevertheless,
even when she's exact, which is the רבנן that argue on רבי
דוסא, Rabbi Dosa, were concerned backwards 24 hours. ואיבעית אימא הכי קאמר,
Ve-iba'it eima hachi ka'amar, if you want here's how you can say
it: לא שכיוונה אלא שפחתה והותירה. lo she-kivna ela she-pachsa ve-hotira.
That's actually to say like רבי דוסא, Rabbi Dosa, we're not talking
about a case when she's exact. When she's exact, you would not
be concerned 24 hours backwards because then we'd assume she bled when
she was expected to. אלא ella, the only case she's concerned backwards
is שפחתה והותירה, she-pachsa ve-hotira, when it was inexact. אבל כיוונה, Aval
kivna, but if it was exact, קבעה לה וסת, she's established a
cycle, דיה שעתה, dayah sha'atah, and she only worries at the moment
she bled. ומני רבי דוסא, U-manni Rabbi Dosa, and this is רבי
דוסא. Rabbi Dosa. So fine, so the גמרא's gemara. basic point is
that a
woman goes 90 days, she, a woman when she's getting older, goes
90 days, she is considered to be מסולקת דמים, mesuleket damim but
that can be obviously
counter-evidence that can be changed once she starts bleeding, but another 90
days will again prove that she's back into that state. And then
it gets into this interesting idea that if she goes 90 days,
90 days, 90 days, we don't say that she keeps on returning
to that state, if it happens three times that establishes a pattern.
Now, by the way, I should say that although the גמרא gemara
makes it sound like when it is exact, it's a bigger חידוש
chiddush to say she's חושש, choshesh, there still is a חידוש chiddush
in the inexact case, because if this woman went first 90 days,
and then 93 days, and then 92 days, or whatever it is,
you could say she's still מסולקת דמים. mesuleket damim, She went 90
days again without bleeding. She doesn't have a fixed pattern. So why
should we assume that she's now regularly seeing? Why don't we just
interpret this as a מסולקת דמים mesuleket damim. again, even if she
doesn't because it's not being replaced by a fixed pattern, it's being
replaced by a non-fixed pattern, 90, 93, 92 and so on. So
that seems to have been another way to read the ברייתא braita
that the גמרא gemara did not adopt, but I'm just mentioning that
there is a חידוש chiddush even in that case of inexact that
we consider her now to no longer be מסולקת דמים mesuleket damim.
even though it's not replaced by a fixed pattern. Okay. So anyway,
that's what we have by the case about the menopausal, post-menopausal woman,
that 90 days establishes that, once she bleeds again, she goes back
to the previous state, but another 90 days can reestablish it. Three
times, then you're back to being considered now to have a to
bleed over longer periods of time. All right. רבי אליעזר אומר כל
אישה שעברו עליה. Rabbi Eliezer omer, kol ishah she-avru aleha. Now, רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says any woman, it doesn't even have to be
a post-menopausal woman, any woman that goes 90 days without bleeding is
considered מסולקת דמים. mesuleket damim. Now, we actually mentioned that it happens
that women can stop having their period based on malnutrition or other
causes, actually we're going to have a case with malnutrition in a
minute. So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said it doesn't have to be
because of menopause, it could be for any reason, if a woman
has gone 90 days without bleeding, whatever the causes are, we assume
she's מסולקת דמים mesuleket damim. until we have evidence otherwise. So let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara We're going to quote a
ברייתא Braisa we quoted before. תניא אמר להם רבי אליעזר לחכמים. Tanya:
Amar lahem Rabbi Eliezer lachachamim. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said to the
sages, מעשה בריבה אחת בהיטלו, ma'aseh bi-rivah achat be-Heitalu, there was a
story with a young woman in היטלו, Heitalu, name of a place,
שפסקה שלוש עונות, she-piska shalosh onot, that she went 90 days without
bleeding, ובא מעשה לפני חכמים, u-va ma'aseh lifnei chachamim, and then she
apparently bled and they came to the Rabbis, ואמרו דיה שעתה, ve-amru
dayah sha'atah, she doesn't have to be concerned 24 hours, she only
has to be concerned from the moment she saw because she's obviously
מסולקת דמים, mesuleket damim, she had gone 90 days without bleeding. אמרו
לו, Amru lo, so the Rabbis said back to him, אין שעת
הדחק ראיה. ein sha'at hadechak re'ayah. That's not a proof, that was
an emergency situation, so they were more lenient, it would not be
the general rule. מאי שעת דחק mai shaat dachak what was the,
sort of, case of urgency? איכא דאמרי שני בצורת הוו ika damri
shnei batzoret havu so some say it was a time of famine.
So you see, on the one hand, the time of famine is
why they didn't want to be so strict as to say 24
hours, because then you'd have to throw out any תרומה truma that
was handled in the last 24 hours by this woman, and who
wants to throw out any food at a time of famine? But
I also think it's significant that if it was a time of
famine, it explains why this woman, this young woman, was stopped menstruating,
because malnutrition is a reason for stopping menstruating. Yes.
The amount of תרומה truma that a person needs to separate for
תרומה truma is actually very, very small.
Well, sure, but if you have thousands of acres of wheat or
whatever, and
that shows how serious this famine must have been.
You mean because if you have a famine, then you don't have
too much wheat, so you don't have too much תרומה. truma. Right,
that's an interesting point. Unless you have תרומה truma left stored up
from last year or something. But that's a good point.
But wouldn't
שעת דחק shaat dachak refer to a national שעת דחק shaat dachak
or do we have...
that's a good point because look at the next line. The next
line is much more of a local שעת דחק. shaat dachak. איכא
דאמרי ika damri some say, no, טהרות נפישא לה עבידה. taharos nefisha
lah avida. No, the שעת דחק shaat dachak was that in this
one case, in the last 24 hours, it happened to be that
she had done a lot of טהרות. taharos. This woman in this
particular case in the last 24 hours had done 100 pounds of
תרומה. truma. So that would be a much bigger consequence of making
her טמאה temeah the last 24 hours than in a normal case.
Entire wheat harvest.
Exactly. So in this case we took the more lenient position, but
it does not mean as a general rule we would agree with
this. As a general rule we would say even if a woman
went 90 days, if there's not a particular issue like she's postmenopausal,
we would not consider her to be מסולקת דמים.
mesuleket damim Yeah, like for instance, you could have plentiful... I'm just
thinking about contemporary... anorexia or whatever it is...
So I'm telling you, the second answer made it clear that even
if it was just because of this particular woman, not a larger
case.
Right. So that means that whatever it is, it's a שעת דחק.
shaat dachak. So in some ways, basically not
disagreeing if you really look at it. Based on the second answer,
then anything would be a... a woman wouldn't normally go 90 days
without bleeding, so it'd have to be a שעת דחק. shaat dachak.
So it would be a ראיה. rayah.
No, no. I was the one that was connecting
the גמרא's Gemara description of the famine to the explanation why she
wasn't bleeding. That was not in the גמרא. Gemara All the גמרא
Gemara. was saying was that the
rabbi, Rebbe, not Rebbe, Rabbi Eliezer said, look, I'll give you a
proof. There was a time the rabbis ruled this, and they said
that was a special circumstance, there would have been a lot of
loss. Okay, they were not at all dealing with the question of
why she wasn't bleeding. Okay, that was not being discussed.
So to me, let's say she wasn't doing a lot of טהרות
taharos and for her reason she was just in dire straits, like
her family had no food, then they would still say that it's...
that I don't know. Maybe that also would be a שעת דחק.
shaat dachak. So that's what I'm saying, if everything is שעת דחק,
shaat dachak, then they're not really disagreeing over anything.
No, they're disagreeing about a case when it's a ten dollar loss
and not a hundred dollar loss, a standard case. That's what they're
disagreeing about.
But what I'm saying is, what's prompting her not to bleed?
Who knows what's prompting her? I have no idea, but that doesn't
necessarily mean it's going to be a שעת דחק. shaat dachak.
The שעת דחק shaat dachak is how big of a loss is
there. That's not necessarily linked to why she's not bleeding, maybe in
some cases it is. Alright, so let's go on.
Yeah, when the woman starts to bleed, anything she touched the
previous...
Yes, what we've been seeing since the beginning of the מסכת, masechet,
and then the question is how do you limit that? Because as
תוספות tosafot has constantly pointed out, there's no way to be careful
for that. So it's a real like... it's a... so that's why
the גמרא Gemara sometimes tries to be more lenient. But yeah, when
a woman bleeds, since we're not certain, maybe she only saw now,
but maybe she started earlier. And particularly because of the הלכה halacha
that a woman becomes טמאה temeah from the time the blood leaves,
passes from the uterus through the cervix into the vaginal canal. So
even before it exits the woman's body, just passes through the cervix,
she's טמאה. temeah. So therefore, you never can know exactly when she
became טמאה. temeah. So there's בית שמאי Beit Shammai actually is quite
lenient and בית שמאי Beit Shammai is one of the places... actually
not בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, שמאי, Shammai, that שמאי Shammai is much
more lenient than הלל. Hillel. He says you don't have to be
concerned about any prior time. But we, actually the sages here, say
that no, even till 24 hours back or till the last time
she checked, whichever is smaller. So that has enormous consequences because there's
no way of protecting against that. So then we are trying to
say all the cases where we wouldn't have to be concerned. But
yeah, but that's exactly why there's like... there's nothing you can do
to prevent this. Okay, what are you going to do, never handle
טהרות? taharos? So it's pretty... you could always check right before a
woman could always check right before she handles...
Last of Rabbi's area was it?
Right,
so yeah, exactly. Alright, so let's take a look. וחשו רבנן להפסד
טהרות vechashu rabanan l'hefsed taharos and the rabbis were concerned about the
loss. תנו רבנן מעשה ועשה רבי כרבי אליעזר maase ve'asa Rebbe k'Rabbi
Eliezer once Rebbe ruled like Rabbi Eliezer that said you don't have
to be concerned 24 hours back and with this woman. לאחר שנזכר
l'achar shenizkar once he remembered that he shouldn't have ruled that way,
אמר amar we've had quoted this before, כדי רבי אליעזר לסמוך עליו
בשעת הדחק. k'dai Rabbi Eliezer lismouch alav b'shaat hadachak. You know what?
We can rely on Rabbi Eliezer even in a... at a time
of urgency.
So it's after the fact, might as well just keep it. psak
פסק paskened *psak*. Mai le'achar shenizkar מאי mai, לאחר שנזכר *Mai le'achar
shenizkar*? What does it mean he remembered? Elima le'achar shenizkar d'ein halacha
k'Rabi Eliezer ela k'Rabbanan אילימא לאחר שנזכר דאין הלכה halacha כרבי אליעזר
אלא Ela, כרבנן *Elima le'achar shenizkar d'ein halacha k'Rabi Eliezer ela k'Rabbanan*,
if he remembered that really we don't rule like Rabi Eliezer רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabi Eliezer*, we reject Rabi Eliezer's רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer. *Rabi Eliezer's* position completely, so besha'at hadachak בשעת הדחק *besha'at hadachak*
heichi avid k'vosei היכי עביד כוותיה *heichi avid k'vosei*? So who cares
if it's a time of like you know pressure of urgency of
a special circumstances if his position is rejected then you can never
rely on it. So ela d'lo itmar halacha lo kemar v'lo kemar
אלא דלא איתמר הלכה לא כמר ולא כמר *ela d'lo itmar halacha
lo kemar v'lo kemar*. It wasn't it wasn't that we completely rejected
his opinion. We didn't have an explicit ruling how we go like.
Umai le'achar shenizkar ומאי לאחר שנזכר *Umai le'achar shenizkar*? And then what
does it mean that he remembered he made a mistake? What mistake
did he make? Umai le'achar shenizkar ומאי לאחר שנזכר *Umai le'achar shenizkar*?
What did he remember? Le'achar shenizkar d'lav yachid palig alei ela rabbim
palig alei לאחר שנזכר דלאו יחיד פליג עליה אלא רבים פליג עליה
*le'achar shenizkar d'lav yachid palig alei ela rabbim palig alei*, once he
remembered you know what it wasn't a one-on-one debate, most of the
positions disagreed with Rabi Eliezer רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. *Rabi Eliezer*. So
although there wasn't like black letter law that we rule against Rabi
Eliezer רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, *Rabi Eliezer*, the normal conclusion would have
been if you would have applied the normal types of ways of
deciding you would have concluded against Rabi Eliezer רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
*Rabi Eliezer* but it hadn't been formally ruled. So he realized that
he should have ruled against it but it wasn't like it was
a formally rejected opinion.
So then he said you know what
kedai Rabi Eliezer lismoch alav besha'at hadachak כדאי רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer.
לסמוך עליו בשעת הדחק *Kedai Rabi Eliezer lismoch alav besha'at hadachak*. It's
a special case I might as well rely on him. Now this
is extremely important I mentioned we had this quoted before because there's
a general idea in halacha הלכה *halacha* which is you know you
can rely on a da'at yachid דעת יחיד *da'at yachid*. One of
the reasons we quote minority opinions is you can rely on minority
opinions besha'at hadachak בשעת הדחק *besha'at hadachak*. But the question becomes well
one question is what do you define as a sha'at hadachak שעת
הדחק *sha'at hadachak*? But the other question is when is it still
a minority opinion and what does it become a rejected opinion? And
you see here that tension in the Gemara גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Is
it ruled that way or is it just the normal conclusion would
have led this way? So for example there's a whole interesting discussion
that comes around you know what happens once the Shulchan Aruch שלחן
ערוך *Shulchan Aruch* rules? How canonical and absolutely authoritative is the Shulchan
Aruch שלחן ערוך *Shulchan Aruch*? And you know if the Shulchan Aruch
שלחן ערוך *Shulchan Aruch* rules against an opinion is it but let's
say it has a lot of support earlier in the Rishonim ראשונים
Rishonim *Rishonim*, does it remain a da'at yachid דעת יחיד *da'at yachid*
that you can rely on besha'at hadachak בשעת הדחק *besha'at hadachak*? Let's
say the Shulchan Aruch שלחן ערוך *Shulchan Aruch* quotes the opinion but
rejects it. Yesh omrim יש אומרים *Yesh omrim* this but this is
the halacha הלכה *halacha*. You know when does something still remain a
minority opinion when is it considered rejected becomes very important and you
see the Gemara גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here is dealing with that balancing
act that it's one thing to say this is how the normal
conclusion would have gone but it's another thing to say we've actually
formally ruled that way and rejected the other opinion. Now what is
the sha'at hadachak שעת הדחק *sha'at hadachak*? So if you say the
sha'at hadachak שעת הדחק *sha'at hadachak* was like this case of a
famine so then the point is but then why did he make
a mistake? It looks like even the chachamim חכמים *chachamim* agree in
a sha'at hadachak שעת הדחק *sha'at hadachak*. So Tosafot תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*
says that it's not as bad as the sha'at hadachak שעת הדחק
*sha'at hadachak* before and actually I mentioned last time Tosafot תוספות *Tosafot*
gives one interesting explanation that the sha'at hadachak שעת הדחק *sha'at hadachak*
had a lot more to do with Rebbe רבי Rebbi *Rebbe* than
the person he was paskening פסקנ'ינג *paskening* for. And Tosafot תוספות *Tosafot*
says that the sha'at hadachak שעת הדחק *sha'at hadachak* was he gave
a ruling and then the person left and the person lived let's
say I don't know three towns over and then when he remembered
if he needed to reverse himself he would have had to go
three towns over to reverse himself. So it was his sha'at hadachak
שעת הדחק *sha'at hadachak* that he didn't want to
schlep שלעפ *schlep* out there.
So that was an interesting explanation of Tosafot תוספות *Tosafot* because if
it was a more serious sha'at hadachak שעת הדחק *sha'at hadachak*, it
seems like even the chachamim חכמים *chachamim* agree that they're willing to
sort of you know be lenient in that type of a case
yes.
Well similar to the Shulchan Aruch שלחן ערוך *Shulchan Aruch* there's the
issue of the Rama's רמ"א *Rama's* rulings.
Well that's what I meant Shulchan Aruch
שלחן ערוך *Shulchan Aruch* Rama רמ"א *Rama*. And you know there are
many cases where we Ashkenazim אשכנזים *Ashkenazim* don't seem to follow the
Rama רמ"א *Rama*.
Yes but that's like you see that's different well you're correct meaning
that gets to the question about how authoritative is the Shulchan Aruch
שלחן ערוך *Shulchan Aruch* when like all a lot of the poskim
פוסקים *poskim* contemporary and immediately after reject the psak פסק *psak* of
the Shulchan Aruch שלחן ערוך *Shulchan Aruch* or the Rama רמ"א *Rama*,
then you could sort of say that never sort of became sort
of established in halacha הלכה *halacha*. But what if there's actually a
position that was followed that was ruled and then followed? You know
to what degree are other positions still viable? But you're right that's
a lot much larger discussion.
Okay just to the.
Well dachak דחק *dachak* literally means pressure. So means like there's somehow
it's extenuating circumstances is a good yes a very good I was
going to say some case of exigency but extenuating circumstances you know
so some that's right.
Next year's Shavuot שבועות *Shavuot* learning.
Right. Tanu Rabbanan תנו רבנן *Tanu Rabbanan*. Tinoket shelo higia zmana lirot
תינוקת שלא הגיע זמנה לראות Tinoket shelo higiah zemana lir'ot. *Tinoket shelo
higia zmana lirot*. Now before we talked about a woman that was
sort of becoming post-menopausal stopping and starting again and so on. Now
we're going to talk at the opposite end about a young girl
who has not yet reached the age of puberty, the age at
which she's expecting her period. Vera'ata וראתה *Vera'ata* and she still sees.
So now pa'am rishona dayah sha'ata פעם ראשונה pa'am rishonah, דייה שעתה
*pa'am rishona dayah sha'ata*. The first time we're not concerned 24 hours
back it was a fluke. Shniya dayah sha'ata שנייה דייה שעתה *Shniya
dayah sha'ata* the second time as well we're not. Why? Normally we
say that once a woman bleeds now we assume that that she
should expect to be bleeding. But this is a woman who even
if she bled she's I mean a woman she's a girl she's
ten years old so it's even after the first time it's a
fluke and we don't say oh now we see she's starting to
get her period because she's not yet of that age. So even
the second time we would not yet be concerned that she should
be expecting her period. However shlishit שלישית *shlishit* by the time she
sees three times even if she's very young then we see that
okay she's getting her period even at a very young age.
V'harei hi kechol hanashim והרי היא ככל הנשים *V'harei hi kechol hanashim*.
Well no, it doesn't seem that that's in a fixed place. We
said before even not fixed. Once it's three times, we see that
it's not we see that she's not מסולקת דמים. mesuleket damim. You
can prove you're not מסולקת דמים mesuleket damim, without having a וסת
קבוע, veseit kavua, right, we said that earlier about the ninety ninety-one
ninety-three and so on. So once she sees three times, we know
that she's
regular, she's not מסולקת דמים, mesuleket damim even though she's very young.
This was also an interesting case because the age has receded over
the centuries.
I think the average age of menarche is what,
I think below twelve, twelve, but it used to be even less.
Right,
yeah, so Charlie mentioned that until 150 years ago,
much nearer for seventeen, seventeen.
But
that's because of malnutrition.
Malnutrition, yeah.
Right, but in the time as Charlie was telling us yesterday, in
the time that the גמרא Gemara. was written, actually the standard of
living was much higher.
So that in the last few decades it's gone down significantly.
Yeah, doesn't that also relate to like also like fast food and
all that other bad stuff people are eating?
McDonald's cheeseburgers are amazing.
Right, that's what I remember hearing.
Hormones and French fries.
Yeah, it's the hormones they
put in the cows.
Oh, interesting.
That's
why
you should
buy organic. Okay, alright. Now okay, moving on. Now, a woman, so
she's not, now I should stop at this moment and say the
גמרא's Gemara going to allude to a debate of רבי Rebbi and
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, which it won't get
into detail here, but we'll get into it later, which is how
many times does a pattern have to repeat to be a חזקה?
chazakah? We normally say three, but that's actually the opinion of רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. רבי Rebbi, says even twice
already establishes a pattern. The גמרא's Gemara going to assume that this
is actually going like רבי, Rabbi because after the second time she's
proven that she's regular, so that for we're concerned by the third
time, we're already concerned that now she is, will have, will be
regularly bleeding, so therefore we're concerned twenty-four hours back after twice. So
although you could have said no, once it's third, the very time
that proves that she's regular is also the time we're concerned backwards.
It's not, you see the point, it's not exactly little clear which
is the pattern. Is the pattern two and therefore we're concerned for
the next time, or is the pattern three and therefore we're concerned
by for the time that the pattern was established? But anyway, we'll
talk about it in the גמרא. Gemara The גמרא's Gemara going to
assume the former, that it happened with two and therefore the third
time we say ah, this was a third seeing that was part
of a regular pattern or part of a woman that's not מסולקת
דמים mesuleket damim, and therefore we're concerned backwards.
So she just saw it like thirty days and after sixty days
and after six months, and we see she's a regular pattern?
Well, not six months, that creates a מסולקת דמים mesuleket damim, again,
but like thirty, forty, twenty, then yes, that's not a regular pattern
of וסת קבוע, but she's no longer מסולקת דמים, mesuleket damim that's
what we saw before. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara goes on
to say the following, the ברייתא braita I should say.
Okay, שלישית הרי היא ככל הנשים ומטמאה מעת לעת ומפקידה לפקידה. shlishis
harei hi ke-chol ha-nashim u-metame me-et le-et u-mifkidah lifkidah. עברו עליה שלשה
עונות, avru aleha shlosha onos, now this woman she went, she's a
woman ten years old. Okay, she saw three months in a row.
Now she went ninety days, and she didn't see. So remember we
saw that ninety days certainly by a woman that's menopause, postmenopausal, and
for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. for any woman, ninety days reestablishes that
you're מסולקת דמים. mesuleket damim. So she went ninety days, so this
ten year old is now back to being מסולקת דמים. mesuleket damim.
וראתה, and she bled
again. דיה שעתה, dayah sha'atah, so it's enough what she saw, she
doesn't have to worry backwards because she goes back to being
מסולקת mesuleket, דמים. ועוד עברו עליה שלשה עונות וראתה, ve-od avru aleha
shlosha onos ve-ra'asah, now another ninety days, so now she goes back
again to being מסולקת mesuleket, דמים. So again, דיה שעתה. dayah sha'atah.
ועוד עברו עליה שלשה עונות וראתה, ve-od avru aleha shlosha onos ve-ra'asah,
another ninety days, so again she went back to being מסולקת mesuleket.
דמים, so again she sees וראתה. Now we don't say דיה שעתה,
dayah sha'atah, because now she went ninety days, ninety days, ninety days,
right, it's like we said before, now she's got a pattern of
ninety days gaps, and therefore הרי היא ככל הנשים ומטמאה מעת לעת
ומפקידה לפקידה. harei hi ke-chol ha-nashim u-metame me-et le-et u-mifkidah lifkidah.
She worries back twenty-four hours. וכשהגיע זמן לראות פעם ראשונה, ve-che-shehigia zman
lir'os pa'am rishonah, now you know what, let me sort of start
illustrating this on the board.
Okay, so here's a woman she's ten years old, young girl. Okay,
so she sees time one, right, and then she is considered still
דיה שעתה, dayah sha'atah, right, because she's still מסולקת דמים that hasn't
proved she's regular, that she is getting her period. Then thirty days,
it's still דיה שעתה, dayah sha'atah, okay. Then here, so we've got
one, two, three, so then it starts saying that now you have
the twenty-four hour wait. Okay, because now she's regular. Okay, then what
happens is she goes ninety days. So she goes ninety days, all
right, and now she
is, now she is again מסולקת, right, if she... She had, so,
okay, so she's מסולקת דמים. So although here she was going 24
hours, now she bled again, and again we say דיה שעתה dayyah
sha'ata because this was a restart. Okay, this is like a reboot.
Okay, because it went 90 days. So even though here she was
waiting 24 hours, here it goes back to דיה שעתה. dayyah sha'ata.
Then another 90 days, so it's another reboot, right? Because here had
she's okay, and therefore again she sees and it's דיה שעתה. dayyah
sha'ata. But she goes another 90 days, so now we have one,
two, three, we have three types of seeing in a pattern, the
same way here we have like three seeing, and even if this
pattern is inexact, you can no longer say it's a reboot because
now we see the 90 days are, even if it's 91 and
93, even if it's inexact, it basically proves that she's this is
not making her מסולקת דמים, it's just very long patterns. So then
she goes back to being 24 hours.
Okay, but if she saw in the middle though, she she had
a 30, but the
גמרא'ס Gemara's going to ask that.
Okay, the reason I'm drawing this is because it's about to get
more complicated.
So let's take a look. That's why there're these huge drawings. Okay,
so anyway let's take a look. Okay, וכשהגיע זמן לראות פעם ראשונה
ukshehiggia zman lir'ot pa'am rishonah now, if she so now she has
90 days, 90 days, 90 days, so when her time so okay
now period. Okay, so that's that. Now let's say it's not a
ten-year-old girl, let's say it's a 12-year-old girl, a 13-year-old girl. הגיע
זמן לראות, higgia zman lir'ot, so she's it's her time where she
would reasonably say she hasn't had her period yet, but her body
is ready. Then פעם ראשונה דיה שעתה, pa'am rishonah dayyah sha'ata, the
first time it still hasn't started yet, so the first time it's
still you don't worry 24 hours back. But שניה, shniyah, by the
second time, this is a this is a girl who's ready to
have her period. So once she sees one, you say now she's
getting her period, so by the second time מטמאה מעת לעת ומפקידה
לפקידה, metame'ah me'et le'et umipkiddah lipkiddah, then you worry 24 hours back.
And the same הלכה, if you start having 90-day breaks. עברה שלשה
עונות וראתה, avrah shloshah onot vera'atah,
if this young girl girl now who is ready to get her
period, she started but then she had a 90-day break, דיה שעתה,
dayyah sha'ata, it goes back to a reboot and it's goes back
to דיה שעתה dayyah sha'ata because now she's מסולקת דמים again. Okay,
now we're going to look at the first case which we drew
up on the board, which is more complicated. אמר מר עברה שלשה
עונות דיה שעתה. amar mar avrah shloshah onot dayyah sha'ata. So when
she went these this first reboot here, this 90 days, דיה שעתה,
dayyah sha'ata, she only had to worry about the time she saw.
So says the גמרא Gemara top of י"ד עמוד א', yud daled
amud aleph, חזרה כחזיא בעונות מאי? hazrah kachazya be'onot mai?
This is Michael's always anticipating the גמרא. Gemara Let's say instead of
here another reboot, let's say here she actually saw after 30 days.
What would be the הלכה? Okay, that's the גמרא'ס Gemara's question. Now
what is this question? Here's let me tell let me frame to
you what the question is.
Okay, a normal girl as we saw וכשהגיע זמן לראות ukshehiggia zman
lir'ot that it's her time that she's already you know of an
age of puberty. Okay, the first time she's not concerned backwards, the
second time she is. This girl, the reason she had three times
before she had to be concerned backwards is because she hadn't gotten
to the age of puberty, right? Are you with me?
So now here, how do we treat this case? She has proven
that she is starting to have her cycle. But then there was
a reboot. At this stage, is her after the reboot, is her
status like a girl who is not at the age of puberty,
because you know physically she's still ten years old, or is her
status like a girl that is at the age of puberty because
we see although there was a reboot, we see from back here
that she does start having her period. So which category do we
put her in, right? When she's saw all three times and then
had the reboot, is she in the category of a girl who
does get you know is of the age or is not of
the age of puberty? What difference would it make? If you consider
her of the age of puberty, so by the second time she
sees she starts worrying 24 hours back. If you consider her not
of the age of puberty, like it was a complete reboot, then
she'll only start worrying 24 hours back until she saw three times.
So this is a reboot, but that's not so interesting. What's obviously
a reboot you're only going to be concerned after a month. The
question is without a reboot, she sees 30 days later. Is this
like a girl under the age of puberty that you're not concerned
by the second time, or is it like a girl of the
age of puberty that you are concerned today? Good question. That's the
גמרא'ס Gemara's question, right?
Let's let's see the answer and then I'll take your question. Okay,
so מאי, what's the הלכה? אמר רב גידל אמר רב פעם ראשונה
ושניה דיה שעתה שלישית מטמאה מעת לעת ומפקידה לפקידה. amar rav giddel
amar rav pa'am rishonah ushniyah dayyah sha'ata shlishit metame'ah me'et le'et umipkiddah
lipkiddah. He basically says that she it is a complete reboot. She's
like a girl under the age of puberty.
So he says פעם ראשונה, this time, ושניה, ushniyah, even if she
bleeds here after 30 days, דיה שעתה. dayyah sha'ata. It's like a
complete reboot, she goes back to being treated as if she's under
the age of puberty, and therefore even the second ראיה re'iyah it's
not a problem. The only time it starts being a problem is
after three.
The same way here one, two, it wasn't a problem backwards until
the third, here too it's a complete reboot so one, two, but
without 90 days would not be a problem backwards until there was
a third.
Even if the third was 90 days later then she'd be back
to מסולקת דמים, right?
Well, that we're going to get to that in a minute. Okay,
but anyway, but that's going to be the next רמב"ם. Rambam. Okay,
so basically you really did not need the 90 days to say
דיה שעתה. dayah sha'atah. ריא"ל Rial and ואחא v'Acha discusses and why
did we give that example? So because you should just say that
makes the pattern and that it's never different. Even after 30 days
is but the complete reboot and it's and it's דיה שעתה.
dayah sha'atah. Yeah.
And those two different situations for first 30, 30?
This? No, no, all the way to the right.
Is that a separate situation or is that part of this?
No, this is all the same girl, the same girl. Okay, so
that's the question. Here it was only a concern backwards after three
times, after this period of 90 days, is that a complete reboot
or not? And the answer is it is a complete reboot. So
therefore you need only the third time you'll be concerned. One, two,
you're still not concerned backwards and only on the third. What's the
logic? What's the logic?
It's still a girl who's under puberty.
So even though this proved maybe the evidence proved that she was
getting her period, but then you had immediate counter-evidence.
So the two sort of balance themselves out.
So you treat the rule that she should
not yet be having her period even though the specific circumstance tells
you otherwise?
No, this circumstance told you otherwise but then she went 90 days
without getting her period.
That's actually normal biology. Is it?
Yeah.
The גמרא Gemara didn't work that way.
Puberty is very rarely regular in general. It could really go like
90 days? Yeah, and that's the normal trajectory.
So these cases are
pretty normal.
If we didn't think that, it would be
we'd be very suspicious of bleeding in a ten-year-old if we didn't
think she was beginning her puberty a little early. Right, right. We'd
think she had an illness. I mean, it would be a problem.
So that's interesting. So it seems like the גמרא Gemara right.
And that's that's logic.
It's it's biology. I would say two things and this came up
yesterday as well. Either the גמרא Gemara like me being a man
didn't know that biology, right? And didn't wasn't aware that that's normal.
So it would have assumed that the fact that it went 90
days proves that it was a fluke and it was not yet
the starting of it. That's one thing, they just didn't know the
biology. The other possibility is and this is an interesting question, maybe
it's going by certain formal rules, you know, despite the biology. So
if you have a formal rule that 90 days determines מסולקת דמים,
you know,
so maybe that just in a formal way counteracts what happened prior.
But I think probably the former has a lot to do with
it as well, at least personally.
And these days, you know, we do
know that alters cycles a lot after the pill now and it
can give you a period maybe three or four times a year.
Right. So a woman could change her status.
Yes. Well, but again as we've seen, if you have your 90
days does not make you מסולקת דמים if you regularly see with
that type of a gap. So you know, you would just have
longer periods but it would not be מסולקת דמים. That's why whenever
it repeats three times you go it's no longer מסולקת דמים. Yeah.
And women are quoted not that infrequently
in ש"ס, Shas, right?
We will see places in נדה Niddah where women are quoted philosophy
is one thing. Yeah, so we'll see though. I mean, it's relatively
frequent it's pretty infrequent even though it's מסכת נדה Masechet Niddah and
when it is we'll see the weight that it's given. So okay.
Although the nature of it being irregular for the first year. I
know.
That's exactly, although see you knew this, like it's like it was
obvious to you, but to me it's a חידוש. chiddush.
I think it's so common. And also I don't have any daughters
I must admit.
Although although
what they're mainly talking about here is
פולטת טהורה. poletet tehorah.
Right, but it's based on the question of do we have to
be concerned that it occurred and is a pattern. Okay, let's keep
on going. Okay, as point is very well
said.
Yeah, go ahead. Isn't it obvious it's still considered prepubescent and דיה
שעתה dayah sha'atah after those 90 days? No, because as we're going
to say in a minute this goes according to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi
Eliezer. So any woman who
was 90 days, you know like we said before, any woman who
hasn't seen for 90
days
is considered דיה שעתה dayah sha'atah even if she's whatever age she
is. Okay. Alright, but it's a good point, but the גמרא Gemara
is going to say it's רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer? Let's keep on
going. וחסדא Vechisda now, the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay, that
was his answer. So was the גמרא Gemara at all concerned with
why? I mean all these הלכות halachot are based on this idea
that you're supposed
to around 30 days have a cycle.
Right. And they know that. They know that.
Why it's not happening for a woman or whether that would be
a problem? Well, the גמרא Gemara does speculate and assumed yesterday or
assumed like oh when she's nursing were you here yesterday? So when
she's nursing it thinks that she's not bleeding because it thinks the
blood is turning into milk. When she's pregnant it thinks she's not
nursing because she thinks the physical weariness of the pregnancy causes the
blood to go away. It did sort of speculate on certain correlations.
Would it associate with disease or anything
like that? Not generally especially if it's something that they sort of
knew occurred. I mean the גמרא Gemara does sometimes talk about מס
חרדה mas charadah fear anxiety. So at what time you mean would
the גמרא Gemara say I think you need to see a doctor?
That's a good point. I don't know of a case like that.
I mean the גמרא Gemara does have a case about somebody who's
bleeding מחמת מכה machmat makah
because of a wound so it does sort of acknowledge that that
can be the case.
So anyway but it's a good... but that's normally when there's some
supporting evidence to indicate that there's some internal wound. Okay so let's
see the גמרא Gemara continues ועוד עברו עליה ג' עונות וראתה. v'od
avru aleha gimel onos v'rasah. So now we're going to the next
period דיה שעתה. daya sha'atah. הדר חזיא באונס מה. hadar chazya b'ones
mah.
So first we asked after this does she go back to being
like pre-pubescent
and what would happen when she bled here? And the answer is
yes she does go back and דיה שעתה. daya sha'atah. Now we're
saying she bled one two and now...
so now the third time after
two 90-day periods after two 90-day periods and then we said after
another 90 days היא דחשישא hi d'chashisha then היא דחשישא hi d'chashisha
backwards. But what if she bled here? Okay what would be the
הלכה there? Meaning what do we say? Do we say this is
again a reboot? So since this reboot what do we say by
this reboot? By this reboot we said she goes
back to being pre-pubescent and it's דיה שעתה. daya sha'atah. So maybe
after this reboot we say the same thing? She goes back to
being treated pre-pubescent
and again it's דיה שעתה. daya sha'atah. Or do we say no
like you can only get one reboot? Okay so if you had
this you can go back to your earlier stage. But now you've
bled three times here bled two
more times we're not going to say even though it went 90
days we're not going to say you go back to being pre-pubescent
and this bleeding we're going to say is now 24 hours. Okay
that's the question. Here we can say after three and then one
this is a full reboot it goes back to 24 hours even
the second time.
So the גמרא Gemara tells a story after that happened twice that
was the question and let's see what the answer is.
אמר רב כהנא אמר רב גידל אמר רב amar Rav Kahana amar
Rav Gidel amar Rav פעם ראשונה דיה שעתה שניה מטמאה מעת לעת
ומפקידה לפקידה. pa'am rishonah daya sha'atah shnia m'tama'ah me'es l'es u'm'pekidah l'pekidah.
And so you're right.
You're right. By this time we're not going to do a full
reboot. So this is going to be דיה שעתה daya sha'atah because
it was after 90 days but here you're no longer considered by
this time you're no longer considered pre-pubescent and by this time a
normal girl who it's her time to be bleeding by the second
time היא דחשישא hi d'chashisha 24 hours now. Okay? So this is
a full reboot you can call it so you go back to
being pre-pubescent so when you do it here it's דיה שעתה daya
sha'atah but this is not a full reboot. This only means this
after this you're considered already to have reached the age of seeing
and therefore it's 24
hours back by the second it is 24 hours now. Not only...
yeah.
Right because it's the second?
Yeah because it's a once we can say the first three were
maybe a fluke.
Rachel's point aside the biology aside but once it's not only you
saw it three times but then you saw it again and again
even though it was this 90-day break clearly you're not at that
stage at all. No it's a reboot in the sense that
in the sense that this is דיה שעתה. daya sha'atah.
If it weren't a reboot at all then it would be 24
hours. Actually it's a good point oh you know what James makes
an excellent point.
Since we see that here even after 30 days it's דיה שעתה
daya sha'atah you don't need a reboot right to get this to
be דיה שעתה. daya sha'atah. Right it's already there which actually supports
why we're waiting here 24 hours right you don't actually need the
service of a reboot.
All right anyway let's go on. But under other circumstances it would.
Anyway let's go on. So the גמרא Gemara says like this all
right that was the hard part it gets easier after this. Okay
מני
רבי היא. mani Rabbi hi. Now who is this? This the fact
that after two times as I said to you the גמרא Gemara
assumes that because
the third time you wait back 24 hours it proves that two
times establishes the pattern okay and therefore that's therefore the third time
becomes a 24-hour concern. So who is that? That's
רבי Rebbi. דאמר בתרי זימני הויא חזקה d'amar b'trei zimni havya chazakah
after twice we've established a pattern. אימא סיפא eima seifa let's look
at the end עברו עליה ג' עונות וראתה avru aleha gimel onos
v'rasah דיה שעתה. daya sha'atah. So it says a girl we've already
been saying 90 days is a reboot. it's even more explicit at
the end. The end it says even when a girl it's her
has hit puberty and it's her time to see and she begins
seeing, with a 30-day break, she goes back to saying דיה שעתה.
daya sha'atah. Not a 30-day, a 90-day break. So who's the opinion
that says that no matter who for all women once it's a
90-day break they go back to דיה שעתה? daya sha'atah? That's רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, right? We could say before that for a post-menopausal
woman 90 days is a reboot, or for a woman that's under
age 90 days is some type of a reboot. But רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer. says for all women 90 days makes her מסולקת, and
that was the case at the end because it said even a
woman, a girl that it's her time to see, after 90
days she's מסולקת. So now it's רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer? So what's
the big deal? So the idea that you go by patterns of
two is רבי. Rebbi The idea that you have a 90-day reboot
is רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. And the problem is if you remember
we said a minute ago that רבי Rebbi basically decided that the
הלכה wasn't like רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer? So how could this משנה
both be רבי Rebbi, and רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer, Okay, different points,
but how could it be that way? So let's take a look.
וכי תימא רבי היא, vechiteima Rebbi hi, that it is רבי, Rebbi,
ובעונה סבר לה כרבי אליעזר, uve'onah savar lah k'Rabbi Eliezer, so the
fact that it says two times establishes a pattern is רבי, Rebbi
the fact that it says 90 days is a reboot, that's רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer. and he rules like רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer, ומי
סבר לה? umi savar lah? He says how can you say רבי
Rebbi rules like רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer והלא אחר שנזכר אמר, vahalo
achar shenizkar amar, it says that רבי Rebbi remembered that he shouldn't
have been ruling like רבי Rebbi. אליעזר. So how could this ברייתא
braita assume both רבי Rebbi, and רבי Rebbi אליעזר? So it goes
the opposite way. אלא רבי אליעזר היא, ela Rabbi Eliezer hi, the
author of the ברייתא is רבי Rebbi, אליעזר, that's the 90-day reboot,
ובוסתות סבר לה כרבי, uvevestos savar lah k'Rebbi, and he holds that
after, but he happens also to פסקן pasken that patterns are established
after two times like רבי. Rebbi Okay, so that's basically the point
of bringing in this very complicated, I mean other than the הלכה
itself, is
that we see that a pattern is established after twice, so the
third time it's considered regular and you wait back 24 hours. And
the fact that 90 days is a reboot even for people, girls
that are at the period where they should be seeing, so that's
רבי Rebbi אליעזר. So part רבי אליעזר, part רבי, and therefore it's
רבי אליעזר who's ruling like רבי when it comes to establishing patterns.
Okay, now we're going to ask some other questions.
As if that wasn't enough.
כתם שבין ראשונה ושנייה טהור. kesem shebein rishona v'shniya tahor.
If a woman sees a
stain, a כתם, kesem,
okay, between ראשונה ושנייה, rishona v'shniya, okay, she
sees a stain, actually
we don't even have to worry about that. Okay, this is a
woman who's not regular, who is not yet a period-seer, a young
girl, right? So until she sees three times we don't assume that
she, we assume it's a total fluke. So if somewhere here she
finds a כתם, kesem, a stain, she saw once, she actually had
her period first time, ten years old, and then she finds a
stain on her garment a month later. So she doesn't have to
assume it came from her. And we've discussed some, it was a
time where we're not talking about inside of a tight-fitting underwear, we're
talking about like on some, you know, inner flap of her garment,
you know, there was blood all around those places between the chickens
they were slaughtering and all this type of stuff, it was not
very hygienic. So there's a reasonable assumption even if you don't know
specifically that it might not have come from her, and since it's
a total fluke you can assume that that's טהור, tahor, okay, between
the first and the second. The question is how about the third?
Because if she actually saw, like we said that after twice you've
established a pattern like רבי, and if you actually saw a third
time, she saw, she would
be assumed it's her and so much as to consider it part
of the pattern and have to be concerned 24 hours back. So
if by the third time she's concerned that she has a regularity,
a pattern, so if she sees a כתם kesem maybe she also
has to be concerned that it came from her? Or maybe not,
maybe until she actually treats her period as regular which happens at
the third time she doesn't yet have to treat her כתם, kesem,
stain, as having come from her. Okay, so that is the question
about seeing a stain between two and three.
So let's take a look.
Okay, שבין שנייה לשלישית. shebein shniya l'shlishis. So what if it's a
stain between second and third? So she's not yet treated any bleeding
as טמא tamei as, you know, part of a pattern, but she
has been, but she's ready to do it because she's done it
twice and she's established a pattern. So חזקיה אמר טמא, Chizkiyya amar
tamei, so we'll treat the כתם kesem like, like an actual, you
know, normal case of seeing blood, and it's
טמא. tamei. רבי יוחנן אמר טהור. Rabbi Yochanan amar tahor. No, I'm
not yet going to attribute it to her, she has not yet
had it three times. חזקיה אמר טמא, Chizkiyya amar tamei, כיון דאילו
חזיא מיטמיא, keivan de'ilu chazya mitamya, so since were she to bleed
she would be טמא, tamei, and not only טמא tamei she's always
טמא tamei when she bleeds, but she'd see that as bleeding as
regular and therefore be concerned 24 hours backwards, not as a fluke.
If she's going to see a third time it would not be
treated as a fluke. So כתמה נמי טמא, kesamah nami tamei, even
when she sees a stain it's going to be seen as coming
from
her and therefore טמא. tamei. רבי יוחנן אמר טהור. Rabbi Yochanan amar
tahor. No, I'm not going to treat the stain yet as טמא,
tamei, it's טהור. tahor. Why? כיון ד keivan de אתחזקה בדם, it-chazka
b'dam,
since she has not yet established a pattern by blood. Now that
sounds like you need three times to establish a pattern, but רש"י
Rashi says, again fitting into the earlier discussion of רבי of two
times, yes, she has a pattern but has not yet been applied.
She has not yet had a bleeding that she has said is
sort of is part of a pattern. Only by the third time,
although it's proven by the second time, it's only sort of treated
as a pattern the third time. So since it has not yet
given that status to real blood, כתמה נמי לא מטמינא לה. ketamah
nami lo matmeina lah. We don't treat כתם ketem as coming from
her. We don't know where it came from yet, and so therefore
since we're not haven't yet treated her bleeding as as regular, we're
not going to treat the the stain as coming from her. Rivka.
Can you repeat about the ten-year-old girl? Just want to make sure
I'm following. So a ten-year-old girl is going to some authority... Right.
Right. Yeah, the ten-year-old girl talking to these rabbis.
Yeah, that's a very good question, how much was this something? So
the גמרא Gemara had a story about two days ago about a
about a maidservant, a slave woman of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel that
had a situation and then went and asked רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel.
But again, that was a maidservant, you know, that was not this
might be very different between mothers and daughters and so on. Right.
Right.
Right. Right. So yeah, I don't know. I don't know if we
have any evidence about, you know, I mean there are...
Are women able to answer these questions?
So you have a גמרא Gemara that discusses the question about women
dealing with identifying whether something is actually red and considered blood or
not, and that's going to come up much later.
Right, exactly. Whether you have the this issue about like women, you
know, sort of saying, oh, in this case you have to be
concerned 24 hours back, in this case you don't. I don't know.
I think we have very few cases of strewn in all מסכת
נדה Masechet Niddah that there that came up to the rabbis about
women's voices. So even as women as asking rabbis שאלות, shailos, you
know, when with how are these cases presented? Were they presented to
other women or were they presented to the rabbis? We can keep
a scorecard. I'm serious. I don't I can't think off the top
of my head. I understand. I understand. Right. So how much were
the women handling this? Look, I I think you're right. I mean
let's count as we're going through the מסכת. masechet. So far we
have one case where רבי's maidservant asked not רבן גמליאל's Rabban Gamliel
maidservant asked him.
Let's that's the only case so far we have of an actual
question being asked. So I think it's a good question, but let's
look for it as we go through. I don't know off the
top of my head the answer to that.
Are women trusted to
report accurately?
Well, that's a general issue. You know, the גמרא Gemara I mean,
the גמרא Gemara in the beginning of what do you call it?
of גיטין, Gittin, you know, and other places establishes the idea that
עד אחד נאמן באיסורין, ed echad ne'eman b'issurin, that you trust one
witness, one person about like is the food you're eating kosher? I
can go to your house, you tell me it's kosher, I can
trust you. And one of the proofs that they give for this,
or one of the proofs is the fact, you know, רש"י Rashi
there says it, is the fact like every single day we trust
our wives when they tell us that they're feeding us kosher food,
you know, and they point to the fact that the תורה, Torah,
that the, you know, נדה niddah is another evidence that we that
women are trusted to deter- to tell what their status is.
But you and I both know that women do not have a
status of an עד. ed.
Right. So the עד אחד נאמן באיסורין ed echad ne'eman b'issurin is
not classic testimony in court. It's basically an issue about believability, and
it's true for women as well, that when it comes to an
issue about is something kosher or טרפה, traif, אסור assur or מותר,
muttar, any person is believed. It's not about formal rules of עדות.
eidus. And one of the classic proof- examples of that is a
woman's believability about her own status vis-à-vis נדה. niddah.
So that actually you're right, that actually but I'm saying, not only
is it true, for many ראשונים that is the sort of foundation
of the principle that you believe one person when it comes to
statuses of kosher, טרפה, traif, אסור assur and מותר, muttar, is the
fact that the woman is believed about her own status as a
נדה. niddah. Yes.
And that issue, does it only apply to people who are above
bar or bat mitzvah age?
Yeah, so that's...
Because then we have ten-year-olds and that's...
Right. All right, I'm going to bracket that. Okay. All right. Now
let's keep on going. מתיב ליה רבי אילא. Metiv lei Rabbi Ila.
So רבי אילא Rabbi Ila asked. וכי מה בין זו ובין בתולה
שדמיה טהורין? V'chi mah bein zo u'vein betulah shedameiha tehorin? So
now חזקיה Chizkiyahu said, right, that if she bled by the third
time the excuse me, she bled twice, we assume the כתם ketem
came from her. Even though she's an underage girl and she has
yet to bleed three times. He says, how is this different than
a בתולה betulah after her wedding night? If she has stains, we
assume those stains are not from her. Because basically we assume a
woman after her wedding night depends on how old she is and
whatever, we'll get to that פרק, perek, but we assume that she's
going to have a certain amount of bleeding based on the hymenal
bleeding. Okay, and therefore if there's a stain, we don't make that
טמא. tamei. So why is it by that woman we assume that
if it's a stain, it's not, you know, she's טהור tahor and
because we said hymenal bleeding, and this woman who is a pre-pubescent...
We are concerned about the stain. Now the answer is obviously different,
and let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. אמר ליה רב
זירא זו שרפא מצוי וזו אין שרפא מצוי. Amar lei Rav Zeira
zu shirfa matzui ve-zu ein shirfa matzui. So first of all, the
metaphor here is the sap, okay? Like, you know, it's a tree
that the sap is running through, that's sort of the metaphor for
the blood for the woman and her menstruation. So it says, by
the virgin, we
actually she is bleeding, but it's not menstrual bleeding, it's hymenal bleeding,
so we can say her כתמים ketamim are טהור tahor because we
could say it came from her, but it was from hymenal blood.
So that's why we can say they're טהור. tahor. This woman, it's
not like she has another source of blood, it's not like she's
got some other reason to be bleeding. And therefore if there's blood,
we'll assume it's from her, there's nothing else you can attribute it
to, so you're going to say that she is טמאה. tme'ah. So
there's a big difference when you have a
concrete other thing that explains where the blood is coming from that's
not טמא tamei as opposed to this woman, although she's prepubescent, she
has bled twice and there's nothing else to attribute it to. Okay.
אמר עולא אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בן יהוצדק. Amar Ulla
amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon ben Yehotzadak. תינוקת שלא הגיע זמנה
לראות. tinokes shelo higia zman liros,
So here I actually say a baby, right? A young girl that
it's not her yet time to see, you know, ten years old
let's say.
וראתה פעם ראשונה ושנייה. Veratah pa'am rishonah u-shniyah. Okay, she saw the
first and second time. So we're back to the bit.
This has not yet been three. Three is from the safe regular
twenty-four hours back. One and two is still rare and a fluke
and not too concerned backwards.
So during that period, let's say we're not dealing with stains, which
is what we dealt with before, but we're going to deal with
something else.
רוקה ומדרסה. Roka u-midrasah. Her spit and places she sat on, okay?
So if a woman is a נדה, niddah, so not only is
she טמאה, tme'ah, again this is not about her status to her
husband, it's about תרומה terumah and such issues. Not only is she
טמאה tme'ah and if she touches things, but her spit is considered
to be an אב הטומאה, av ha-tumah, you know, as טמאה tme'ah
as she is, and same places she sits on. What would be
the status of those types of those things בשוק? bashuk? You found
them in the marketplace, okay? So the question is, the same way
and you don't know, she doesn't know, you don't know when that's
from, okay? So somehow, I don't know how, somehow you know it
was from this woman that this place she sat on, place she
spat, but she doesn't know whether at that time she was a
נדה niddah or not.
והוחזקה בשתי ראיות? Ve-huchzekah bishtei re'iyot? What? Between two times being a
חזקה, chazakah, so it's between two and three?
Right,
presumably it's between two and three. That would make the question more
interesting, okay? So it's between two and three and you don't know
whether it was during the time that she was טמאה tme'ah or
not during the time that she was טמאה. tme'ah.
ברשות הרבים, Bi-reshut ha-rabim, so what's the question? Well, ספק טהור, safek
tahor,
right?
Right, that's partly it. תוספות also says that if it's בשוק bashuk
as opposed to just in terms of the practical issues, you know,
there's more it's
there's more reason to sort of just have no idea when it
came from and just be a much bigger doubt, okay?
But ספק טומאה ברשות הרבים safek tumah bi-reshut ha-rabim is enough to
say that it's ספק טהור. safek tahor. So we don't even need
any this whole regular case. Since זה ספק, zeh ספק, when you
say ספק טהור?
safek tahor? Yeah, but as we've seen, the
גמרא Gemara is irregular, excuse me, about when it applies the principle
ברשות הרבים ספיקו טהור bi-reshut ha-rabim safeko tahor by a נדה. niddah.
Okay, so anyway let's take a look. So גמרא says, so בשוק
טהור. bashuk tahor. I'm sorry, כתמן נמי טהור. ketaman nami tahor. Okay,
so because we'll be lenient by the מדרס midras in the שוק,
shuk, we'll be lenient by the כתם. ketem. Now there's a big
difference. The מדרס midras in the שוק, shuk, the question
is, did she sit on this thing or spit when she was
a נדה niddah or not when she was a נדה? niddah? Right,
by the כתם, ketem, the question is, did it come from her
or not come from
her? So, you know, there's a it's not exactly comparable, but anyway
he makes the comparison, okay? And
he says her כתם ketem is טהור, tahor, even between two and
three. So ולא ידעינן אי דידיה אי דרביה. Velo yadeinan i dideih
i de-rabbeih. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said in the name of
רבי שמעון בן יהוצדק, Rabbi Shimon ben Yehotzadak, we don't know if
it's רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan himself or whether he's just saying in
the name of his rebbe. למאי נפקא מינה? Lemai nafka mina? What
difference does it make? למהוי דבר של אחד במקום שניים. Lemehavi devar
shel echad bi-mekom shnayim. So whether it's going to be two against
one.
Because before we had רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and חזקיה Chizkiyah debating
whether the כתם ketem is טהור tahor between two or three. If
here it's not only רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan but also his rebbe,
then it's רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and his rebbe against חזקיה Chizkiyah
and they win, two against one. But if it's if it's really,
you know, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan himself, then it's not two against
one.
Okay. So now the גמרא says,
let me just check for one minute.
Right, okay. So now the גמרא goes on. כי אתא רבין וכל
נחותי ימא, Ki ata Ravin ve-chol nechutei yama, when רבין Ravin came
from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and all those that went down to
the sea, whatever that means, some big group of people that went
presumably from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to בבל, Bavel, אמרוהא כרבי שמעון
בן יהוצדק. Amruha ke-Rabbi Shimon ben Yehotzadak. They said that this ruling
that the כתם ketem is טהור tahor between two and three, they
said that that was straight רבי שמעון בן יהוצדק Rabbi Shimon ben
Yehotzadak and it was not, you know, and therefore it was a
third opinion to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan himself. Meaning, actually, I think
I misexplained it. Here, clearly, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying in
the
name of רבי שמעון בן יהוצדק. Rabbi Shimon ben Yehotzadak. That
when רבי יוחנן... Rabbi Yochanan... Anyway, they said that there was
distinct positions. There was a decision of רבי שמעון בן יהוצדק Rabi
Shimon ben Yehozadak and there was a position of רבי יוחנן Rabi
Yochanan and it was two
against one. And therefore we rule that the כתם ketam is טהור.
tahor. אמר רב חילקיא בר טובי, Amar Rav Hilkiya bar Tuvi, so
now we're onto a
slightly different topic, let's see if we can get to the two
dots. אמר רב חילקיא בר טובי: Amar Rav Hilkiya bar Tuvi: תינוקת
שלא הגיע זמנה לראות, this young girl that has not yet regular,
has not yet started seeing, אפילו שופעת כל שבעה אין אלא ראייה
אחת. afilu shofas kol zayin ein ela reiah achas. Let's say she
bleeds for seven days straight. So remember,
if she bleeds three times, then you decide that now she is
regular and now she'll start, she's considered to be 24 hours back
and so on. Let's say she bleeds over seven days. Is that
one time or three times?
Is she considered a זבה? zavah?
No, because it was within seven days. Okay, more than seven days
you start worrying about זבה. zavah. So he says that's once. So
that seems pretty obvious. The גמרא says, אפילו שופעת, afilu shofas, you
mean even if she's bleeding constantly, talk about needing to go to
a doctor.
ולא מיבעיא פוסקת, v'lo mibaya posekes, it goes without saying if she
breaks, it's sounding
like if she breaks it's obviously one ראייה. reiah. The opposite makes
sense. If she's bleeding on and off, you're more likely to count
it as multiple.
אדרבה, the opposite makes sense. פוסקת הוי כשתי ראיות. posekes havei k'shtei
rei'os. If she breaks it should be like multiple seeings. She saw
day one and day three and day seven, maybe that counts as
seeing three times. So אלא, okay you're right, here's what you should
say. תינוקת שלא הגיע זמנה לראות ושופעת כל שבעה אין אלא ראייה
אחת. tinokes shelo higia zman liros v'shofas kol zayin ein ela reiah
achas. If she's bleeding constantly, not אפילו שופעת, afilu shofas, if she's
bleeding constantly, that counts as once. If she's bleeding one day and
stops a day and another day and stops a day and another
day, even though it's all within like a week, that's considered three
separate times and therefore she's now considered regular. Which is a little
funny obviously because we all know the, you know, biology is that
it's all the same period. It's not like it's proving more regularity
even if it's starting and stopping.
But she'd have to wait eight days,
she'd be a זבה קטנה. zavah ketanah. אמר רב שימי בר חייא:
Amar Rav Shimi bar Chiya: מדלפת אינה כרואה. midalafes eino k'roeh. If
a woman is just, if it's just coming out not flowing, but
not stop and start, but like dripping. You know, a little bit,
a little bit, it's continuous but it's a little bit, it's not
a flow. That's not like
she saw. So what do you mean it's not like she saw?
You mean she's טהור? tahor? והא קחזיא, v'hakachazya, she saw! She's obviously
טמא. tamei. אימא אינה כשופעת, eima eina k'shofas, no what I mean
is, is that it's not like the case of flowing, אלא כפוסקת,
ella k'fosekes, it's like stopping and starting. So here you have basically
what would occur every single time, a woman gets her period, woman,
young girl, ten years old, right, as long as it's not flowing,
if it goes over three days even if it's like a little
gradual throughout, as long as it's not a flow, that's considered to
be with a little break, that's considered to be separate ראיות rei'os
and now she's considered regular. So the גמרא says, מכלל דשופעת כנהרא?
michlal d'shofas k'neharam? So what, the one case where it's considered one
ראייה reiah is when she's flowing like a river? So you know,
the גמרא sort of recognizes that that's absurd. What woman has that,
you know, flows that degree? And talk about again, talk about having
to see a doctor. אלא אימא, ella eima, so no what I
mean to say is, and he changes it again, אינה אלא כשופעת.
eina ela k'shofas. So yes, if she's sort of, if it's sort
of, you know, coming out gradually and dripping and so on, that's
what we mean by flowing. And we don't mean she has to
flow like a river. So now we're saying if a woman gets
her period, woman, young girl, ten years old, gets her period, it's
over a few days, if it's like constantly flowing, again not flowing,
you know constantly dripping or whatever, then it's considered one ראייה.
reiah.
But if there's breaks, you know periods of not seeing and then
starting again, that's multiple and that makes her regular. Again it's pretty
funny.
Does she have to wait the 30 days?
She doesn't have to do the whole 30 days. It's very strange.
We would say in order to be regular you need to wait
a minimum number of days to be considered like a new period.
So here the גמרא is being very formalist that with some break
it's already
considered like another ראייה. reiah. How small can the breaks be? Yes,
it's not clear, I assume at least a day. I'm just going
to finish up to the two dots. תנו רבנן חזקה בנות ישראל
עד שלא הגיעו לפרקן הרי הן בחזקת טהרה אין נשים בודקות אותן.
tanu rabbanan chazaka bnos Yisrael ad shelo higiu l'pirkan harei hen b'chezkas
tahara ein nashim bodkos osan. So before they girls have gotten to
their, to puberty, they're considered not to assume that they might bleed
and nobody has to check for them. And here's the נשים בודקות
אותן, nashim bodkos osan, not בודקות bodkosing but helping them see if
they're bleeding. Women, nobody has to worry about them. We
assume they're not bleeding if they're prepubescent. משהגיעו לפרקן, mishehigiu l'pirkan, once
they hit puberty, הרי הן בחזקת טומאה, harei hen b'chezkas tumah, doesn't
mean that they're טמא tamei but it means we have to be
concerned they might be bleeding, right, because you know we've פסק before,
you bleed, you check twice a day and you check before this
and you check before that. There was so much checking going on
that as soon as a girl hits puberty she has to be
worried that she might be getting her period. ונשים בודקות אותן v'nashim
bodkos osan and other women will help check her to see if
she's gotten her period. So you know talk about being able to
have that sort of private... so talk about being able to have
that sort of private time instead of dealing with changes of your
body here as soon as a woman as a girl gets to
that period because of the concern of touching טומאה tumah and טהרה
taharah touching תרומה Trumah or whatever all these other women are getting
involved maybe it means her mother but whatever helping her check to
see if she's gotten her period.
And so also the teacher.
It could be the teacher, right? רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer
אין בודקין אותה ביד ein bodkin osa beyad they don't actually
manually check her, מפני שמעבבות אותן mipnei sheme'avavos osun because that actually
sort of can be damaging, which might mean it might rupture the
hymen, or it might mean that they can scratch her inside and
cause bleeding not based on
what's actually happening. Right. Exactly. Right. That's what I thought. It's maybe.
אלא, here's what you do. Let's just finish this point. סכות אותן
בשמן Sachos osan beshemen what they do is they actually sort of
give her a rub down with oil
מבפנים mibifnim and sort of inside, okay, you know, ומקנחות אותן מבחוץ
umkanachos osan mibachutz and wipes it outside. I'm not exactly sure what
you're wiping if the oil was on the inside, maybe the oil's
outside and inside. So it's a rub down with oil and also
goes inside.
והן נבדקות מאליהן Vehen nivdakos me'aleihen and then and if they're ready
to bleed somehow in the process you'll see her bleeding and you
do it without actually doing a manual check. But there's still... yeah,
I don't get it. Go in on that high note. Another...